Finding Aid for Charles A. Hill Family Papers 1917-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles A. Hill Family Papers 1917-1981, 1939-1970
Hill family.
2.7 linear feet
9977 Aa 2
Charles A. Hill was African American pastor of Hartford Memorial Baptist Church in Detroit, Michigan; collection includes church materials, scrapbooks and photographs, information collected about Hill and his activities by the Detroit Police Department, and family information.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection was a gift of Bermecia Hill Morrow McCoy, on behalf of the Charles A. Hill Family (Donor no. 8855 ) in July 1999.
Collection is open to research.
Rev. Charles Andrew Hill, Sr., was born in Detroit on April 28, 1893, to Mary Lantz Hill, a German-American woman, and Edward Hill, an African-American dentist. His father settled in Chicago to establish himself while Charles was still young, and his mother was left to try to raise him alone. As a result of the lack of opportunities for women at the time, Charles spent some years in a city orphanage while his mother tried to attain financial security. He graduated from Cleary Business College in Ypsilanti in 1912, from Lincoln University of Pennsylvania (where he received formal religious training) in May 1919, and Moody Bible College in Chicago.
Ordained in 1918, Hill served for a short period as assistant pastor under Rev. Robert L. Bradby at Second Baptist Church in Detroit. Unhappy with automotive companies' use of Detroit's Black churches (including Second Baptist) as labor clearing houses for "anti-union" employees. Hill found this practice unacceptable and resigned his post to take leadership in 1920 of Hartford Avenue Baptist Church. He remained at Hartford until his retirement in 1969. Under his ministry, Hartford grew in size from 35 members in 1920 to well over 1,000 members in 1945 and became one of the largest African-American churches in Detroit.
During that period, Hill maintained his commitment to the labor movement, which in part also led to his strong ties to the civil rights movement. He was active in marches and demonstrations to increase public housing and job opportunities for African-Americans in Detroit. He also served on the Executive Board of the Michigan Council of Churches, the Civic Committee of the Baptist Ministerial Conference, the Sojourner Truth Citizens Committee, the Citizens Committee for Jobs for Negro Women, and the Mayor's Race Relations Committee after the 1943 race riot. He worked to build coalitions among labor leaders and groups, the Civil Rights Federation, the NAACP and diverse religious and ethnic communities within the city. He was nominated an honorary member of the Ford Local 600, and in 1942 was elected president of the Detroit Chapter of the NAACP. Because of his active involvement in civil rights and labor issues, he was unjustly labeled a "Red" and "communist dupe," and he was repeatedly called before the House Committee on Un-American Activities. Additionally, the Detroit "Red Squad" or Criminal Intelligence Bureau maintained kept a series of files on him, which are included in this collection.
Despite public and personal attacks on his character, Hill and his wife, Georgia, were very highly regarded among family, friends, and church and community. The Hills, married in 1919, raised eight children together: Charles A. Hill, Jr.; Roberta Walden; Lovica Broom; James Wesley Hill; Bermecia Morrow McCoy; Lantz Hill; Sylvia Overstreet; and Brendt Hill. Charles Hill passed away February 8, 1970, and Georgia Hill passed away September 19, 1983.
The Charles A. Hill Family Papers are comprised of 2.7 linear feet and range in date from 1970 to 1981. The collection focuses primarily on the life and work of Charles A. Hill, Sr., although papers concerning other family members are also included. The collection is arranged into four series: Hartford Avenue Baptist Church, Charles A. Hill and Family, Red Squad Files, and Scrapbooks/Photographs.
Subjects:
Afro-American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-American clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Race relations.; Hartford Memorial Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); Hill family.; Hill, Charles A. (Charles Andrew), 1893-1970.; Hill, Georgia.; National Association for the Advancement of Colored People. Detroit Branch.; Police--Michigan--Detroit--Records and correspondence.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Afro-American churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-American clergy--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Afro-Americans--Spiritual life--Michigan--Detroit.; Baptists, Black--Michigan--Detroit.; Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.; Hartford Memorial Baptist Church (Detroit, Mich.); Hill family.; Hill, Charles A. (Charles Andrew), 1893-1970.; Hill, Georgia.
Contributors:
Hill, Charles A. (Charles Andrew), 1893-1970.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Hartford Memorial Baptist Church
  The Hartford Memorial Baptist Church series (.4 linear feet) includes records from 1946 to 1986 and consists primarily of programs, anniversary brochures, and historical material documenting the life of the church and of Rev. Hill. Also included is a folder of papers on Judge George and Dr. Ethelene Crockett, who were active and highly regarded in both the church and community.
  - 26th Anniversary of the Pastorate of Charles A. Hill 1946 (Box 1)
  - 45th Anniversary Brochure 1962 (Box 1)
    (includes pastor's 42nd anniversary)
  - 49th Anniversary Program, Missionary Society 1967 (Box 1)
  - Booster, 1931-1961 (Box 1)
  - Crockett, Judge George and Dr. Ethelene (Box 1)
  - Historical 1931 (Box 1)
  - Legal/correspondence 1920-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Programs
    - 50th Anniversary 1967 (Box 1)
    - 65th Anniversary, Ladies Aid Society 1986 (Box 1)
    - Anniversary of Pastorate of Charles Hill 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Opening of New and Enlarged Hartford Avenue Baptist Church 1945 (Box 1)
    - Various 1951, 1961-1968 (Box 1)
- Rev. Charles A. Hill and Family
  The Charles A. Hill and Family series (.6 linear feet) includes records from 1917 to 1997. This series contains primarily materials related to Charles Hill, Sr., particularly his civic and political work. Also included are papers from Georgia Hill, Charles Hill, Jr., the Morrow McCoy family, and the debutante balls attended by Hill's granddaughters in the 1960s. Of particular interest is the volume of minutes of meetings from the Detroit Chapter of the NAACP in the 1940s, during which time Hill was president.
  - Biographical 1920, 1952-1986 (Box 1)
  - Civic and Political 1940-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Debutante Balls 1963-1969 (Box 1)
  - Diplomas and Certificates 1917-1968, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Family Miscellaneous 1968-1981 (Box 1)
  - Hill, Charles Jr. 1950-1951, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Hill, Georgia (Box 1)
  - Morrow-McCoy Family 1970, 1985, 1993, 1997 (Box 1)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, Detroit Chapter Minutes of meetings 1944-1947, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Red Squad Files
  The Red Squad Files series (1.0 linear feet) is comprised of three albums kept by Detroit's "Red Squad" or Criminal Intelligence Bureau. Documents included in these albums date from 1939 to 1970 and include CIB memos on meetings and events attended by Charles and Georgia Hill, "activity cards" on their involvements and support of various causes, newspaper clippings, and other materials associated with the Hills, such as programs from the Hartford Avenue Baptist Church and campaign flyers from Charles Hill's bids for Detroit Common Council.
  - Charles Hill: Clippings, programs, etc
    - 1939-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1970 (Box 2)
  - Georgia Hill: Clipping
    - 1967 (Box 2)
  - Charles and Georgia Hill Red Squad Files
    - 1939-1970, 5 parts (in 3 volumes) (Box 3)
- Scrapbooks / Photographs
  The Scrapbooks/Photographs series (.7 linear feet) is comprised mainly of materials formerly maintained as scrapbooks. Created by the family or groups within the church, these volumes (now stored in folders) contain documentation relating to various facets of the Hills' lives. Most of the volumes were given to Hill as presentation gifts in commemoration of his various anniversaries within the church. The first volume includes papers related to the Hartford Avenue Baptist Church, including photographs, church programs and newsletters, and newsclippings. The second volume entitled "Georgia Hill and Trips, etc." includes photographs, newsclippings, and certificates of recognition of Georgia Hill. The third volume entitled "Behold--The Man" is a photo album of Charles Hill, and also includes a few photos of Georgia Hill and her parents. The fourth volume entitled "Personal and Family Births & Deaths" is an extensive family scrapbook, including photos, certificates of appreciation, church programs, poems and dedications to the Hills, legal documents related to lawsuits filed by Charles and Georgia Hill, birth and death records, and other documents. Of particular interest is the short biography of Charles Hill, written by a doctoral student, and a lengthy hate letter addressed to Charles Hill in 1964. The last volume is a scrapbook of Charles Hill's retirement, including newspaper clippings from throughout his life, photographs, biographies, and letters of well-wishing from various organizations and individuals. Also included as part of this series is one folder of copyprints of photographs depicting Hill as pastor and performing various church functions. There is also a file photocopied photographs of the Hill family, from Charles in early adulthood through his great-grandchildren in their childhood. The family retains the originals to all of these photographs
  - Scrapbook containing copies of church bulletins Boosters publication, and programs of various Hill church anniversaries, 1929-1967 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook entitled "Georgia Hill and Trips, etc." and containing photographs, clippings, and memorabilia (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook entitled "Behold--The Man" containing portraits and informal photos of Hill from different periods in his life (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook entitled "Personal and Family Births & Deaths" containing clippings, photographs, and other documents (Box 2)
  - Retirement commemoration volume containing photographs, correspondence, clippings, and other materials 1968 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (photoprints of originals) of Hill and family, and of church functions circa 1920-1950 (Box 2)
  - Photographs (photocopied) of Hill and Hill family members circa 1900-1985 (Box 2)